<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

<channel>
<title>Susam's OpenSource Maze</title>
<link>https://susam.in/maze/</link>
<atom:link href="https://susam.in/maze/rss.xml"
           rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>Feed from Susam's OpenSource Maze</description>

<item>
<title>Hacktoberfest Spam</title>
<link>https://susam.in/maze/hacktoberfest-spam.html</link>
<guid>https://susam.in/maze/hacktoberfest-spam.html</guid>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<p>
  I received two pull requests for two of my projects on GitHub today.
  I am the author of one and the maintainer of the other.
</p>
<p>
  At first, the pull requests did not make sense at all. One of them
  made minor changes to a README, e.g., changing "this book" to "the
  book". It did not fix a typo or grammatical error. It merely chose a
  word different from the one I had chosen. In fact, I preferred "this
  book", so the pull request (PR) was inconsistent with my preference.
  There was no explanation whatsoever regarding why this change was
  warranted. Then I looked at the pull request author's profile and
  found that the same person had submitted several such trivial pull
  requests to other projects too, all of them changing "this" to "the"
  at some places in various README files.
</p>
<p>
  It all began to make sense when I looked at the calendar. It was Oct
  01. This looked like pull request spam due to Hacktoberfest. For
  now, I just labelled the pull requests as "invalid" (as suggested by
  the <a href="https://hacktoberfest.digitalocean.com/faq/">Hacktoberfest
  FAQ</a>), closed the pull requests, and moved on.
</p>
<p>
  Like all good things created with good intentions on the Internet,
  spam is hurting this event and bringing bad reputation to it. The
  possibility of large scale, endless spam should be worked into the
  design of any new Internet-based event or solution.
</p>

<p><a href="https://susam.in/maze/hacktoberfest-spam.html">Read on website</a></p>
]]>
</description>
<pubDate>Thu, 01 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Non-Commercial Licenses Are Non-Free Licenses</title>
<link>https://susam.in/maze/non-commercial-licenses-are-non-free-licenses.html</link>
<guid>https://susam.in/maze/non-commercial-licenses-are-non-free-licenses.html</guid>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<p>
  I have had to explain this a couple of times on various forums, so I
  thought it would be good to write a post about it and explain why
  non-commercial licenses are non-free licenses. Some examples of
  non-commercial licenses
  are
  <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">CC BY-NC</a>,
  <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">CC BY-NC-SA</a>, and
  <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">CC
  BY-NC-ND</a>. These are all non-free licenses.
</p>
<p>
  The fact that non-commercial licenses happen to be non-free licenses
  appear to be counterintuitive to some. Isn't prohibiting the usage
  of some artefacts for commercial purpose good for free artefacts?
  Maybe it is. May be it is not. That is irrelevant while deciding
  whether a license is considered free or not. What is relevant though
  is whether the license satisfies the principles laid out in some of
  the widely followed principles of freedom in creative work.
  Especially in the context of software, such as for licensing
  artefacts related to software development and usage, we have a few
  widely accepted guidelines that we can refer to:
</p>
<ul>
  <li>
    <a href="https://www.gnu.org/philosophy/free-sw.en.html">Free
    Software Definition (FSD)</a>
  </li>
  <li>
    <a href="https://www.debian.org/social_contract">Debian Free
    Software Guidelines (DFSG)</a>
  </li>
  <li>
    <a href="https://opensource.org/osd">Open Source Definition
    (OSD)</a>
  </li>
</ul>
<p>
  Note that when we say "free" here, we mean free as in speech, not
  free as in beer. Prohibiting commercial usage of some work violates
  these principles of software freedom mentioned in the documents
  referenced above:
</p>
<ul>
  <li>
    <p>
      Freedom 0 of the Free Software Definition (FSD): The freedom to
      run the program as you wish, for any purpose (freedom 0).
    </p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>
      Point 6 of the Debian Free Software Guidelines (DFSG): No
      Discrimination Against Fields of Endeavor: The license must not
      restrict anyone from making use of the program in a specific
      field of endeavor. For example, it may not restrict the program
      from being used in a business, or from being used for genetic
      research.
    </p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>
      Point 6 of the Open Source Definition (OSD): No Discrimination
      Against Fields of Endeavor: The license must not restrict anyone
      from making use of the program in a specific field of endeavor.
      For example, it may not restrict the program from being used in
      a business, or from being used for genetic research.
    </p>
  </li>
</ul>
<p>
  By the way, the OSD was originally derived from the DFSG. That is
  why the OSD looks quite similar to the DFSG.
</p>
<p>
  So what does this all mean and why should you care? The
  non-commercial licenses are good at doing what they are meant to do,
  that is, prevent commercial exploitation of your work. If that is
  what you want, the non-commercial licenses are perfect for you. But
  it is worth noting that restricting non-commercial usage does come
  at the cost of unhindered collaboration. For example, a work
  licensed under CC BY-NC, CC BY-NC-SA, or CC BY-NC-ND cannot be
  remixed, adapted, or relicensed with work licensed under the CC BY
  or CC BY-SA.
</p>
<p>
  If you want unhindered
  collaboration, <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC
  BY</a> is one of the most permissive licenses available from
  Creative Commons. There is
  also <a href="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">CC0</a>
  which gets as close to public domain as
  possible. <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">CC
  BY-SA</a> is another good option if you want to ensure that one
  cannot remix your work into some proprietary work and redistribute
  it. But note that even CC BY-SA requires that you do not impose any
  additional restrictions to the license terms. That is, even CC BY-SA
  allows commercial usage and is incompatible with any non-commercial
  license.
</p>

<p><a href="https://susam.in/maze/non-commercial-licenses-are-non-free-licenses.html">Read on website</a></p>
]]>
</description>
<pubDate>Sun, 22 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Immediate SourceForge Tracker Notification</title>
<link>https://susam.in/maze/immediate-sourceforge-tracker-notification.html</link>
<guid>https://susam.in/maze/immediate-sourceforge-tracker-notification.html</guid>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<p>
  Here are the steps I followed to prevent the tracker email notification
  sent to a SourceForge mailing list address from being held for
  moderation.
</p>
<ol>
  <li>
    Navigate to <em>Mailman admin</em> &gt; <em>Privacy options</em>
    &gt; <em>Sender filters</em>. Then
    add <code>noreply@sourceforge.net</code> to the list of non-member
    addresses whose postings should be automatically accepted.
  </li>
  <li>
    Navigate to <em>Mailman admin</em> &gt; <em>Privacy options</em>
    &gt; <em>Recepient filters</em>. Then
    add <code>noreply@sourceforge.net</code> to alias names (regexps)
    which qualify as explicit to or cc destination names for this
    list.
  </li>
</ol>
<p>
  The first step was necessary because all emails sent by tracker
  has <code>noreply@sourceforge.net</code> as the <em>From</em> address.
</p>
<p>
  The second step was necessary because all emails sent by tracker
  has <code>noreply@sourceforge.net</code> as the <em>To</em> address.
</p>

<p><a href="https://susam.in/maze/immediate-sourceforge-tracker-notification.html">Read on website</a></p>
]]>
</description>
<pubDate>Tue, 13 Apr 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>OSVDB in GSoC</title>
<link>https://susam.in/maze/osvdb-in-gsoc.html</link>
<guid>https://susam.in/maze/osvdb-in-gsoc.html</guid>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<p>
  The Open Source Vulnerability Database (OSVDB) is participating in
  Google Summer of Code (GSoC) this year. I have been contributing to
  OSVDB as a <em>vulnerability mangler</em> since Aug 2006 and
  analyzing new vulnerabilities being published by security
  researchers, adding more details to them depending on the nature and
  severity of the vulnerabilities, and cataloging them. Our internal
  systems for cataloging vulnerabilities could use some help from more
  contributors, so it is great that OSVDB is participating in GSoC
  this year.
</p>
<p>
  Last month we selected some potential contributors from a pile of
  applications. One of them is Timothy F. Tutt Jr. who will be doing
  the Researcher Confidence Project for OSVDB.
</p>
<p>
  In the commenting system for OSVDB contributors, Brian Martin a.k.a.
  Jericho, one of the project leaders, wrote this comment that I found
  quite funny:
</p>
<blockquote>
  Don't think I need to argue how big this is to me, given the time I
  spend arguing with researchers and vendors. If we approve this and I
  am not the mentor, I will feed Jake to a woodchipper.
</blockquote>

<p><a href="https://susam.in/maze/osvdb-in-gsoc.html">Read on website</a></p>
]]>
</description>
<pubDate>Fri, 27 Apr 2007 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Volunteering for OSVDB</title>
<link>https://susam.in/maze/volunteering-for-osvdb.html</link>
<guid>https://susam.in/maze/volunteering-for-osvdb.html</guid>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<p>
  I am now an active Open Source Vulnerability Database (OSVDB)
  volunteer. I joined it on 06 Jun 2006. Although I enrolled as a
  volunteer there around 3 weeks, I worked on a vulnerability for the
  first time today. The vulnerability I picked for my first
  contribution
  was <a href="https://cve.mitre.org/cgi-bin/cvename.cgi?name=2006-2971">0verkill
  recv_packet() Function UDP Handling Overflow DoS</a>. This is an
  integer underflow error in a Linux based gaming daemon called
  0verkill. It could be exploited to launch DoS attacks by sending UDP
  packets of size less than 12 bytes to the 0verkill daemon. An
  example exploit code is available
  at <a href="http://web.archive.org/web/20201208191904/https://www.securityfocus.com/archive/1/436659/100/0/threaded">this
  Bugtraq thread</a>.
</p>
<p>
  OSVDB is a project of the Open Security Foundation. Its goal is to
  provide accurate, unbiased information about security
  vulnerabilities in computerized equipment. The core of OSVDB is a
  relational database which ties various information about security
  vulnerabilities into a common, cross-referenced data source.
</p>
<p>
  In OSVDB, vulnerability reports, advisories, and exploits posted in
  various security lists enter the database as new entries. Each new
  entry contains only a title and links to entries of the same
  vulnerability in other security lists. However, a new entry does not
  contain any detailed description of the vulnerability. After the new
  entries are thoroughly scrutinized, analyzed, and refined by us, we
  add vulnerability description, technical description, solution
  description, manual testing notes, etc. Then these details on each
  entry are reviewed by other members of OSVDB, further refined if
  necessary, and then marked as stable entries. Once an entry for a
  vulnerability becomes stable, the detailed information for it
  appears on the page for the entry. One of the wonderful things that
  OSVDB brings to the world of security research is that each entry
  published on the OSVDB website has an extensive and almost
  exhaustive list of cross-references linking together all information
  about the vulnerability available on various security databases.
</p>

<p><a href="https://susam.in/maze/volunteering-for-osvdb.html">Read on website</a></p>
]]>
</description>
<pubDate>Sat, 24 Jun 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
</item>


</channel>
</rss>
